仕分け[しわけ]:assortment journalizing (in bookkeeping)/classification, よろしく:well/properly|best regards
（フィー）
ハチ 仕分けのほう よろしくね
Okay, Hachi, get started
on the sorting work.
I'll come right down to help out
once I'm done with the paperwork.
手続き[てつづき]:procedure/(legal) process/formalities, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close, 手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to
（フィー）手続き 終わったら
すぐに私も手伝うから
I copy.
コピー:copy/photocopy
（ハチマキ）アイ コピー
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation), 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 早々[そうそう]:as soon as.../just after...|hurriedly, 早々[はやはや]:quickly, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
ったく 帰った早々 仕事 仕事って
Damn it, they put us to work
right after we got back...
十[じゅう, とお]:ten, 十[シー]:ten, 休む[やすむ]:to be absent|to rest|to go to bed|
（タナベ）
十分 休んだじゃないですか
Come on, you got
plenty of rest.
In a hospital bed.
病院[びょういん]:hospital
（ハチマキ）病院でな
（タナベ）でも いいことも
あったんじゃないですか？
It wasn't all bad,
though, right?
I don't wanna play tag
with ninjas ever again.
忍者[にんじゃ]:ninja (persons in feudal Japan who used ninjutsu for the purposes of espionage, assassination, sabotage, etc.), 追いかける[おいかける]:to chase/to run after/to pursue, なんざ:what star sign? (astrology)/what constellation?
（ハチマキ）
忍者と追いかけっこなんざ―
二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol)
二度とごめんだね
No, that that.
I meant the girl in the hospital.
病院[びょういん]:hospital
（タナベ）そうじゃなくて
病院の子のほうですよ
Yo.
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender
（男性１）よう
（タナベ）ん？
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, 休暇[きゅうか]:holiday/day off/furlough, 終わり[おわり]:the end
（男性１）
テクノーラさん 休暇は終わりか？
Hey, Technora guys.
Vacation's over?
早速[さっそく]:at once/immediately/without delay, こき使う[こきつかう]:to work (someone) hard/to push (someone) around
（ハチマキ）
ああ 早速 こき使われてるよ
Yep, and they didn't waste any time
in working us like dogs again.
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather
（男性２）
しかし すんげえ拾ってきたな
Still, you guys came back with a huge haul.
That's Toy Box for ya.
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger
さすが ToyBox(トイボックス)
は？
She's Fee-san's ship, right?
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, フィー:phi, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
（男性２）
フィーさんの船だろ？ これ
はい
Right.
She's the best there is when it comes to
piloting. Giving retrieval instructions, too.
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, ピカイチ:scoring hand in hanafuda with one 20 point flower card and six 1 point flower cards, 操船[そうせん]:handling a ship, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 指示[しじ, しし]:indication/denotation|instructions
（男性２）
ピカイチだよな 操船も回収指示も
I hear she even turned down Vega
when they tried to scout her.
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, 社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc., スカウト:scout, 断る[ことわる]:to refuse|to inform|to ask leave
（男性１）ベガ社からのスカウトも
断ったんだって？
Yeah, I heard, I heard.
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender
（男性２）ああ 聞いた 聞いた
フィー:phi, 結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||, 有名人[ゆうめいじん]:celebrity/public figure/big name
フィーさんって
結構 有名人だったんだ
I didn't know Fee-san
was such a celebrity.
Yeah. In this biz, nobody can
even come close to Fee.
業界[ぎょうかい]:business world/business circles/(the) industry, 飛びっ[ひ]:rook, 切り[きり]:end|bounds|delivery date (of a futures contract)||, 優秀[ゆうしゅう]:superiority/excellence, フィー:phi
ああ この業界じゃ
飛びっ切り優秀だよ フィーは
Of course, it doesn't look like the top brass
have caught on to that little fact.
もっとも:most/extremely, もっとも:but then/although|reasonable, 連中[れんちゅう, れんじゅう]:company/lot|troupe, ちっとも:not at all (neg. verb), みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
もっとも 上の連中は ちっとも
分かってないみたいだけどな
♪～
時空[じくう]:space-time, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 夢を見る[ゆめをみる]:to dream/to have a dream
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
静寂[せいじゃく, しじま]:silence/stillness/quietness, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
鳥[とり]:bird|bird meat (esp. chicken meat)/fowl, 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
儚い[はかない]:fleeting/transient|empty (dream, etc.), 生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 燃やす[もやす, もす]:to burn
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
幾[いく]:some|many|how many?, 幾[ほとほと]:quite (usu. negative connotation)/utterly/really, 千[せん, ち]:1,000/thousand, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||
♪幾千の朝に
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
♪光が向かう場所へ
羽ばたく[はばたく]:to flap (wings)|to spread one's wings/to go out into the world
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
果て[はて]:the end/the extremity/the limit, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
フロンティア:frontier
♪フロンティアへ
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
Phase 8
A Place to Cling to
Surely neither Vega or Ogorico are quite
that hard pressed for human resources...
Mind if I sit here?
（フィー）ここ いい？
（ドルフ）ん？
久しぶり[ひさしぶり]:a long time (since the last time)/it's been a while (since I last saw, mailed, etc., you)
お久しぶり
Long time, no see.
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation
（社員１）何だ？ あの女
Who's the woman?
She's with Half Section,
isn't she?
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（社員２）半課のやつだろ？
I bet she's trying to suck up
to the division manager.
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 売る[うる]:to sell
事業部長に
こび売ってんじゃないの？
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation
（社員１）ケッ
I ran into Chad
on the moon.
チャド:Chad, 経理課[けいりか]:accounting section, 配属[はいぞく]:assignment (of a person to somewhere)/attachment (of a person to another unit, organization, etc.)
月で チャドに会ったわ
経理課に配属になってた
He'd been assigned to
Accounting Section.
預かる[あずかる]:to look after|to take charge of|to reserve (judgment)
これ 預かってきたんだけど
He asked me to keep this for him.
He said he found it when he moved.
引っ越し[ひっこし]:moving (dwelling, office, etc.)/changing residence, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
引っ越しで見つけたんだって
Really takes you back,
doesn't it?
懐かしい[なつかしい]:dear/desired/missed
懐かしいわね
But it looked like Chad wasn't getting
along as well as he did back then.
チャド:Chad, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
でも チャド あのころみたいには
いかないみたい
That's right.
Things aren't the same now.
（ドルフ）
そうだ あのころとは違う
（フィー）ん？
ちょうど:exactly/precisely|as if, ちょうど:supplies/furniture/fixtures, 話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language), ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
ちょうどよかった
君に話しておきたいことがある
Actually, you came at a good time.
There's something I want to discuss with you.
あっ…
All right, we'll leave the arrangements for
the welcome reception to you, Lavie.
歓迎会[かんげいかい]:welcome party, 仕切り[しきり]:partition|settlement of accounts|preliminary warm-up ritual|
（ゲイハート）
じゃ 歓迎会の仕切りは―
任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||
ラビィ君に任せるということで
任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（ラビィ）
はっ お任せください
Yes, sir! Leave everything
to me, sir!
We're only bringing you in to make sure
the guest is kept happy,
接待[せったい]:reception/welcome|wining and dining, 置く[おく]:to put|to leave (behind)|to establish (an organization, a facility, a position, etc.)||
（社員）接待のためだけに
君を置いているんだから―
...so we don't want to see
any slip-ups.
間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman)
間違いのないように
Of course not!
そりゃあ:very/extremely|that is
そりゃあ もう デヘヘヘッ… ん？
場合[ばあい]:case/situation
（ラビィ）あちっ… って
どうすりゃいいのよ この場合
Ouch!
What am I supposed to do
in a situation like this?!
ばかばかしい:absurd/ridiculous/silly
（ハチマキ）
何言ってんだよ ばかばかしい
What're you saying?
What a load of crap.
振る[ふる]:to wave|to sprinkle|to cast (actor)||, 振る[ぶる]:assuming the air of .../behaving like ...|to put on airs, ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation)
ネタ 振ってんな ったく…
Don't go around
spreading rumors.
It's the truth, I swear!
Fee and the
division manager were sitting all alone!
本当なんだって
フィー:phi, 事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, っきり:only/just|since
フィーと事業部長が２人っきりで…
リストラ:(corporate) restructuring/downsizing, 相談[そうだん]:consultation/discussion
リストラの相談でも
してたんじゃねえの？
You sure they weren't talking over
downsizing plans or something?
（課長）ええっ！？
リストラ:(corporate) restructuring/downsizing, 人事[じんじ]:personnel affairs/human affairs/human resources, 人事[ひとごと, たにんごと]:other people's affairs/somebody else's problem
リストラなら 人事だろ？
Downsizing would be
Personnel Section, right?
Why would the division manager himself talk
to a Half Section team leader about that?
わざわざ:expressly/specially/doing something especially rather than incidentally, 事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 主任[しゅにん]:person in charge/senior staff/manager, 伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
わざわざ 事業部長様が
半課の主任に伝えるか？
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), プライド:pride
半課って言うなよ プライドねえな
Don't call us Half Section!
Where's your pride?
I couldn't hear what they were saying,
but she handed him a thin piece of paper.
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
話は聞こえなかったけど―
薄っぺら[うすっぺら]:very thin/flimsy/cheap, 紙[かみ]:paper, 紙[し]:newspaper, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, 渡す[わたす]:to ferry across (e.g. a river)|to lay across|to hand over
薄っぺらな
紙みたいな物を渡してた
Paper?
Like a letter?
紙[かみ]:paper, 紙[し]:newspaper, 手紙[てがみ]:letter
紙って 手紙ですか？
In this day and age?
A disk, maybe?
今どき[いまどき]:these days/nowadays|at this time (of the day), ディスク:disk, 写真[しゃしん]:photograph/photo|movie
今どき？ ディスクとか？
（課長）写真
A picture!
チケット:ticket, お金[おかね]:money
何かのチケット
（ユーリ）お金
A ticket to something!
Money?
お金[おかね]:money, 手切れ金[てぎれきん]:consolation money/compensation for breaking off relations (e.g. with a mistress)/settlement
お金？ 手切れ金！
Money...?
Separation money?!
つきあう:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあう:to poke each other/to jab each other
（課長）
あの２人って つきあってたの！？
Those two were seeing
each other?!
Of course not! Fee-san is married
and even has a son!
（タナベ）
そんなわけないじゃないですか
フィー:phi, 結婚[けっこん]:marriage, 子供[こども]:child/children
フィーさん
結婚して 子供もいますよ
So she's having an affair? This isn't...
不倫[ふりん]:adultery/immorality/impropriety, マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|
不倫ってこと？ マズいな
だから 違いますって！
You've got it all wrong!
What kind of relationship
do they have, then?!
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
じゃあ どういう関係なのよ
なさる:to do
うわっ ごめんなさい
I'm sorry!
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, いただく:to receive/to get|to eat
（エーデル）時間ですので
帰らせていただきます
It's quitting time, so I'm going to
call it a day, if you don't mind.
（ラビィ）はあ
Okay...
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|
（エーデル）
それでは お先に失礼します
Now, if you'll excuse me.
Good work today...
お疲れさま[おつかれさま]:thank you/many thanks|that's enough for today
（タナベ）お疲れさまでした
I must admit,
it does seem odd.
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
確かに おかしいですね
Yeah, people our age
spying like this.
（ハチマキ）いい年して
こんなことやってる俺たちがな
やっぱり:too/also|still, 手切れ金[てぎれきん]:consolation money/compensation for breaking off relations (e.g. with a mistress)/settlement
やっぱり 手切れ金じゃ…
It's got to be a
separation payment.
違いますよ
It is not! Fee-sama is married
and even has a...
フィー:phi, 結婚[けっこん]:marriage, 子供[こども]:child/children
フィーさんは
結婚して 子供もいるんですから
関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
そういうのって
関係ねえんじゃねえの？
Stuff like that doesn't have
anything to do with it.
関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
そういうのって
関係ねえんじゃねえの？
はい？
Excuse me?
ほんと:truth/reality|proper, 好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
ほんとに好きになったら―
When you're in love, stuff like kids or husbands
are the last thing on your mind, right?
ほんと:truth/reality|proper, 好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
ほんとに好きになったら―
子供[こども]:child/children, 旦那[だんな]:master (of a house, shop, etc.)|husband (informal)|sir||, すっ飛ぶ[すっとぶ]:to rush off/to rush away/to vanish, じまう:to do something completely
子供とか旦那とか
すっ飛んじまうもんだろ？
Are you speaking
from experience?
経験[けいけん]:experience, 談[だん]:talk/story/conversation
経験談ですか？
一般[いっぱん]:general/universal|ordinary, 論[ろん]:argument|theory (e.g. of evolution)|essay
一般論だよ
I'm just speaking
in general.
Then are you saying that Fee-san
is having an affair, Senpai?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, フィー:phi, 不倫[ふりん]:adultery/immorality/impropriety
じゃあ 先輩は フィーさんが
不倫してるって言うんですね？
What are you so mad about?!
These things happen.
怒る[おこる, いかる]:to get angry|to tell someone off|to be angular, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
何 怒ってんだよ
そういうこともあるって話…
もう いいです！
I've had enough!
一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, フィー:phi, 無実[むじつ]:absence of the fact|innocent|false, 証明[しょうめい]:proof/verification/certification, みせる:to show/to display
私一人でも フィーさんの無実を
証明してみせます！
I'm gonna go prove Fee-san's innocence!
By myself if I have to!
Hey! Where are you going?! Tanabe!
（ハチマキ）
おい！ どこ行くんだよ タナベ
（課長）どうしよう ラビィちゃん
What should we do, Lavie-chan?
Leave it to me, Chief. Now is the time
to put my networking skills to use.
任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one, 課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief
お任せください 課長
人脈[じんみゃく]:personal connections
今こそ 私の人脈を使うときです
（ハチマキ）
ちょっと待てって おい
Hey, wait up,
damn it!
（タナベ）どうしてですか？
Why should I?
Won't asking the division manager directly be the fastest way to find out?
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 直接[ちょくせつ]:direct/immediate/personal, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
事業部長に直接 聞いたほうが
早いじゃありませんか
（ハチマキ）アホか？ お前は
- What are you, an idiot?!
As if he'd tell you the truth!
正直[しょうじき]:honesty/integrity|honestly, 話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
正直に話すわけないだろ？
（クレア）どいてくれる？
（ハチマキ）ん… あ あっ
Would you mind
stepping aside?
Um, you're...
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ...
ああ えーっと…
It's Claire Rondo of Control Section,
Tanabe Ai-san of Half Section.
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), ロンド:rondo, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
（クレア）
管制課のクレア･ロンドよ
半課の田名部(たなべ) 愛(あい)さん
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
デブリ課です！
It's Debris Section!
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, なさる:to do
ここは管制課よ
用がないなら 半課に帰りなさい
This is Control Section. If you don't have
any business here, go back to Half Section.
用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|
（タナベ）用なら あります
We have business here, all right! We're here
to ask the division manager something!
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
事業部長に
聞きたいことがあるんです
H-Hey!
おっ おい
Ask him if he's been having
an affair?
不倫[ふりん]:adultery/immorality/impropriety
（クレア）不倫したかどうか？
（タナベ･ハチマキ）えっ？
大声[おおごえ, たいせい]:loud voice
あれだけ大声 出してればね
You were speaking
rather loudly.
You really shouldn't stick your nose
into the private matters of strangers.
他人[たにん, ひと]:another person|unrelated person (i.e. not related by blood)|outsider, プライバシー:privacy, 口を挟む[くちをはさむ]:to cut into (a conversation)/to interject
他人のプライバシーに
口を挟むもんじゃないわよ
Understand, Tanabe-san
the rookie?
半人前のタナベさん
他人[たにん, ひと]:another person|unrelated person (i.e. not related by blood)|outsider
（タナベ）他人じゃありません
We're not strangers.
What are you, then?
Don't try to tell me you're friends.
（クレア）じゃあ 何？
仲間とか言わないでよ？
What's wrong
with that?
いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good, やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（タナベ）いけませんか？
（ハチマキ）おい やめろって
Come on, cut it out.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 黙る[だまる]:to be silent, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
先輩は黙っててください
You stay out of this, Senpai!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
先輩？
"Senpai"?
It sounds like you think you're still
a student in an after-school club.
学生[がくせい]:student (esp. a university student), 学生[がくしょう, がくそう]:Heian-period student of government administration|Buddhist scholar|learning, サークル:group with a common interest (e.g. students)/club (e.g. company sports club)/circle, 気分[きぶん]:feeling/mood, 抜ける[ぬける]:to come out|to fade|to wear a hole (e.g. clothes)||, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
学生のサークル気分が
抜けてないみたいね
A company isn't
a family.
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family
会社は家族じゃないのよ
割り切る[わりきる]:to find a clear solution/to come to a clean decision|to divide, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
そんな割り切り方 愛がありません
There's no love in coldly
dividing people up like that!
遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|, シスター:sister, 目指す[めざす]:to aim at/to have an eye on|to go toward
（クレア）
フンッ 今からでも遅くないわ
シスターでも目指したら？
You know, it's not too late. Why don't
you try to become a nun or something?
（チェンシン）アッハハハ…
That's one interesting girl.
She actually held her own against Claire?
面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant, 互角[ごかく]:equality/evenness/par, 言い合う[いいあう]:to say to each other/to exchange (jokes, comments, etc.)|to quarrel, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（チェンシン）面白い子じゃないか
クレアと互角に言い合えるなんて
She doesn't have
the brains for that.
頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||
（ハチマキ）
あいつに そんな頭はねえよ
All she's got in her head is that
idiotic, superficial notion of love.
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 上っ面[うわっつら]:surface/appearances, なぞる:to trace (drawing)/to follow
愛 愛って バカみたいに
上っ面 なぞってるだけだよ
ふーん:hmm/well ...|roughly
（チェンシン）ふーん
押しとどめる[おしとどめる, おしとめる]:to check/to stop/to keep back
（ハチマキ）
あのあと 押しとどめるのだって…
Afterwards, she said she'd try
to keep it under control.
負ける[まける]:to lose|to succumb|to be inferior to||
ああっ くそ！ また負けた
Crap, I lost again!
So, did you talk to Claire
about anything?
話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
（チェンシン）
…で クレアとは何か話した？
意外[いがい]:unexpected/surprising, 意地[いじ]:stubbornness|disposition|appetite, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
意外と意地 悪いのな お前
You've got a surprising mean
streak in you, you know that?
Breaking up because with her, just
because of your father isn't good.
父親[ちちおや]:father, 原因[げんいん]:cause/origin/source, 別れる[わかれる]:to part (usu. of people)|to separate (of a couple)|to lose (e.g. one's mother), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
父親が原因で別れるなんて
よくないよ
Even breakups need
a good, solid reason.
別れる[わかれる]:to part (usu. of people)|to separate (of a couple)|to lose (e.g. one's mother), きちんと:properly/accurately|neatly, けじめ:distinction (e.g. between right and wrong, public and private, etc.)
別れるにしても
きちんとけじめつけて
何度[なんど]:how many times?/how often?, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
何度も聞いたよ その話
I've heard that from you
a million times...
初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ..., 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
じゃあ 初めてする話
Then let's talk about
something new.
About Tanabe-san... Does she have
her eye on anyone in particular?
決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes), 相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.)
タナベさんって
決まった相手 いるのかな？
はあ？
あっ…
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
“お仕事 頑張って”か…
"Keep working hard," huh?
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 移動[いどう]:movement/transfer|mobile, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, 係長[かかりちょう]:chief clerk
管制課に移動してもらう 係長だ
I'm going to transfer you to Control Section.
As the manager.
冗談[じょうだん, ぎだん]:jest/joke/funny story, 管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
冗談 管制課なんて
Control Section?
You must be joking.
補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance, 飛ばす[とばす]:to fly|to skip over|to run or drive fast||, いきなり:abruptly/suddenly/all of a sudden, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|
それも補佐とか すっ飛ばして
いきなり係長？
Plus, you'd make me manager, skipping over
being an assistant manager first?
現場[げんば, げんじょう]:actual spot/scene|shop floor, 合う[あう, おう]:to come together|to fit|to be profitable|
私には現場が合ってるって
I belong out in
the field.
I want someone who knows
what it's like out there.
現場[げんば, げんじょう]:actual spot/scene|shop floor, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
その現場を知る人間が欲しい
There's a limit to what
you can do out there.
現場[げんば, げんじょう]:actual spot/scene|shop floor, 限界[げんかい]:limit/bound
現場でやれることには限界がある
我々[われわれ]:we, 社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc.
だから 我々は
テクノーラ社にいるのだろう？
That's why we're in Technora,
isn't it?
理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive
（フィー）
テクノーラにいる理由ね
The reason we're in Technora, huh...
What is it again? I forget.
なんでだっけ？
Excuse me...
（タナベ）あの…
うっ ぐっ…
いきなり:abruptly/suddenly/all of a sudden
な… 何だ？ いきなり
Don't sneak up on me
like that!
教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
あの… 教えてほしいことがあって
Um... I was hoping you could
tell me something.
聞ける[きける]:to tell
ああ…
ハチには聞けないこともあるよな
Oh. I guess there are some things
you can't ask Hachi.
Actually...
その…
ギャハッ！
Who is having an affair
with whom?!
不倫[ふりん]:adultery/immorality/impropriety
（フィー）誰が誰と
不倫してるって？ あん？
すいません すいません
I'm sorry, I'm sorry!
I hear you've been asking around about me.
They said you were calling it networking.
あちこち:here and there/all around|to get things in the wrong order (back to front), 回る[めぐる]:to go around|to return|to surround|, 回る[まわる]:to turn|to visit several places|to function well|
あちこちに聞いて回ったそうだな
人脈[じんみゃく]:personal connections
人脈とか言って
全面的[ぜんめんてき]:all-out/general/over-all, 全[ぜん]:all/whole|pan-, 方位[ほうい]:bearing/heading/point of the compass, 的[てき]:-like/typical, 的[まと]:mark/target, 全力[ぜんりょく]:all one's power/whole energy, 全開[ぜんかい]:opening fully/full throttle, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, ござる:to be
（ラビィ）私が全面的 全方位的
全力全開で悪うございました
In every way, shape, and form,
what I did was wrong!
（フィー）たく…
Geez, it's a sad story when the people
you work with don't trust you.
信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 情けない[なさけない, なっさけない]:miserable/pitiable/shameful, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
仲間に信じてもらえないなんて
情けない話だ
言い訳[いいわけ]:excuse|explanation
俺は別に…
（フィー）言い訳するな！
I didn't do anything.
Spare me the excuses!
（課長）んっ
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself
タナベ てめえ！
Damn it, Tanabe!
Well, you guys were going around
with the wrong impression.
勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, 勘違い[かんちがい]:misunderstanding/wrong guess
だって みんな勝手に勘違いして…
チクる:to tattle/to tell on/to inform a superior of someone's actions
（ハチマキ）
だからって チクることねえだろ！
That doesn't mean you
should go squeal on us!
チクる:to tattle/to tell on/to inform a superior of someone's actions
チクるって…
"Squeal" on you?
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
…で 結局 事業部長とは
何の話だったんですか？
So anyway, what was it that you were
talking about with the division manager?
昔話[むかしばなし]:old tale/folk tale|reminiscence
ん？ ああ ただの昔話だよ
We were talking about the old days, that's all.
We were coworkers back in our old company.
同僚[どうりょう]:coworker/co-worker/colleague, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace
同僚だからな 前の会社の
（ユーリ）え？
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace
前の会社？
Old company?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation
あっ！ トラウム宇宙開発
Oh! Traum Space Development!
何です？ それ
What's that?
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, 事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, つくる:to make/to produce|to prepare (food), ベンチャー:venture
（ラビィ）昔 事業部長がつくった
ベンチャーだよ
A venture company the
division manager founded.
As I recall, it was acquired and absorbed
into Technora about 10 years ago...
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 吸収[きゅうしゅう]:absorption/suction/attraction, 合併[がっぺい, ごうへい]:combination/union/amalgamation
確か 10年前に
うちに吸収合併されたんだっけ？
つくる:to make/to produce|to prepare (food)
みんなで つくったんだ
We all founded it together.
Dolf brought the four of us together.
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 引っ張る[ひっぱる]:to pull|to string (lines)|to pull towards oneself (e.g. someone's sleeve)||
ドルフが
私たち４人を引っ張ってさ
We were small, but it was a great company
that pulled together like a family.
小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny
小さいけど―
家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family, まとまる:to be collected/to be settled/to be in order, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace
みんな家族のようにまとまった
いい会社だった
不倫[ふりん]:adultery/immorality/impropriety
いやあ 不倫じゃなくて
よかった よかった
Wow, I'm so relieved that it
wasn't an affair.
I can only hope that you refrain
from having any affairs, too, Ai-chan.
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, よろしく:well/properly|best regards, 不倫[ふりん]:adultery/immorality/impropriety, 勘弁[かんべん]:pardon/forgiveness/forbearance
愛ちゃんも よろしくね
不倫は勘弁して
Senpai is the one you should
be saying that to, sir.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
私より先輩に言ってください
Oh, he won't be a problem.
Women don't go for his type at all.
ああ こいつは大丈夫
全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely, モテる:to be popular (esp. with the opposite sex)/to be well liked/to be pampered (spoiled, doted upon, etc.), タイプ:type/kind/sort
女には 全然 モテないタイプだから
Actually, it looks like
he has a girlfriend.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
先輩には 彼女がいるみたいですよ
Is that true, Hachi?!
そうなのか？ ハチ
Ha-chan, who is she?
I won't stand for any affairs, got it?
相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.), 不倫[ふりん]:adultery/immorality/impropriety, 困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered
ハッちゃん 相手は誰？
不倫は困るよ 不倫は
なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
いねえよ 彼女なんて
I don't have
a girlfriend.
病院[びょういん]:hospital, カード:card
病院でカードやってた子は？
Then what do you call that girl you were
playing cards with in the hospital?
What are you, nuts?
That girl's only 12 years old.
歳[さい]:-years-old|ability/gift, 歳[とし]:year|age|past one's prime
何言ってんだよ
あの子は まだ12歳だぞ
But she was taller
than you!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great
先輩より大きいのに？
Some 12 year olds
are like that.
歳[さい]:-years-old|ability/gift, 歳[とし]:year|age|past one's prime
いるんだよ そういう12歳も
ルナリアンじゃないんですか
Oh, she isn't a Lunarian,
is she?
ルナリアン？
Lunarian?
It means humans who were
born on the moon.
生まれる[うまれる]:to be born
月で生まれた人間のことですよ
They grow extremely tall
as a result of the low gravity.
重力[じゅうりょく]:gravity/gravitation/gravitational pull, 背[せい]:height/stature, 背[せ]:back|reverse|height|, 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive
低重力なので 背が高くなるんです
へえ
体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult
じゃあ 体は大人なんだろ？
But she has the body
of an adult, right?
Stop talking like a pervert,
old man!
らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish, 言い方[いいかた]:way of talking/speaking style, おやじ:first character (of a dictionary entry), おやじ:one's father/old man/one's boss
やらしい言い方すんな おやじ
Don't get so
worked up.
ムキになる:to become serious/to take something seriously (joke, teasing)/to become irritated or angry (usu. at something trivial)
んな ムキになるなよ ん？
Why, hello there,
Chief Gehrhart.
課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|
（ラビィ）
これは これは ゲイハート課長
Has there been a change in plans
for the welcome reception?
歓迎会[かんげいかい]:welcome party, 変更[へんこう]:change/modification/alteration, 点[ちょぼ, チョボ]:dot/point|gidayuu musicians (in kabuki)
歓迎会に何か変更点でも？
Don't try to pull any political
maneuvering with me.
つまる:to be packed (with)/to be full (space, schedule, etc.)|to be blocked (road, pipe, etc.), 画策[かくさく]:plan/scheme/program formulation
（ゲイハート）
つまらない画策などするな
はっ？
Sir?
You came to me yesterday to ask
about the division manager.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager
（ゲイハート）昨日 私に
事業部長のことを聞きに来たな
件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item
（ラビィ）
ああ その件でしたら もう…
Oh, that! That's
all been sorted...
You wanted to show off that you have a
pipeline to the division manager, didn't you?
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, パイプ:pipe/tube
（ゲイハート）
事業部長とのパイプを―
誇示[こじ]:ostentation/display
誇示したかったというわけだな
考え[かんがえ]:thinking|idea|intention||
あの… 私 そんな考えは何も
Um... The thought never
crossed my mind.
You don't know?
（ゲイハート）知らないのか？
（ラビィ）は？
Sir?
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), フィー:phi
（ゲイハート）事業部長は
半課のフィー･カーマイケルを―
The division manager wants to assign Half
Section's Fee Carmichael to Control Section.
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 配属[はいぞく]:assignment (of a person to somewhere)/attachment (of a person to another unit, organization, etc.)
管制課に配属するつもりだ
I'm Section Chief there,
and he didn't even consult me.
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 相談[そうだん]:consultation/discussion, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 待遇[たいぐう]:treatment/reception|working conditions
課長の私に何の相談もなく
それも係長待遇でな
And he's going to make her
Assistant Chief, too!
か！？
通称[つうしょう]:popular name/nickname/alias, ゴースト:ghost
（クレア）
Dbr-068-2114 通称“ゴースト”
Dbr-068-2114.
AKA "Ghost."
The debris is a special material
with stealth properties that was expelled from
an INTO lab module.
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 実験[じっけん]:experiment, モジュール:module, 流出[りゅうしゅつ]:discharge/outward flow|leak of (private) information or pictures, ステルス:stealth, 性[さが, なりくせ]:one's nature/one's destiny|custom, 性[せい]:nature (of a person)|sex|gender|, 特殊[とくしゅ]:special/particular/peculiar, 素材[そざい]:raw materials/subject matter
連合の実験モジュールから流出した
ステルス性の特殊素材です
レーダー:radar, 反応[はんのう, はんおう]:reaction/response
レーダーには反応しない
It doesn't show up on radar. Which means that
we only have a rough idea of its position, right?
大ざっぱ[おおざっぱ]:rough (as in not precise)/broad/sketchy, 位置[いち]:place/situation/position, つかめる:to seize/to catch|to obtain
つまり 大ざっぱな位置しか
つかめないってことか
We'll give you an estimated position based on the
orbital data we collected while it was on dayside.
昼[ひる]:noon|daytime|lunch, 側[そば, そく]:near/close|third person, 側[がわ, かわ]:side (of something, or taking someone's side)/part|(watch) case, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, データ:data/datum, 予測[よそく]:prediction/estimation, 位置[いち]:place/situation/position
昼側の間につかんだ軌道データで
予測位置を出します
But you expect us to eyeball it when we're
making the retrieval itself, right?
回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 目視[もくし]:eyesight/seeing
でも 回収そのものは
目視でやれってことでしょ？
In addition, as you can see here, it expands
and becomes unstable at high temperatures.
しかも:moreover/furthermore|nevertheless, 高温[こうおん]:high temperature
（クレア）しかも
高温では このように―
膨張[ぼうちょう]:expansion/swelling/increase, 不安定[ふあんてい]:instability/insecurity/crankiness, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation
膨張して
不安定な状態になります
So please carry out the retrieval on nightside,
where the temperatures are low.
回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal
ですから回収は―
低温[ていおん]:low temperature, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
低温になる夜側で
行ってください
It doesn't show up on radar, and you
can only catch it at night...
レーダー:radar, 映る[うつる]:to be reflected/to harmonize with (harmonise)/to come out (photo), 夜[よる, よ]:evening/night, 夜[や]:counter for nights, 捕まる[つかまる]:to be caught|to hold on to|to find (e.g. proof)|
レーダーに映らない夜しか
捕まらない
It's just like a ghost,
all right.
まさしく:surely/no doubt/evidently, ゴースト:ghost
まさしく ゴーストだね
Debris teams at other companies have
made several attempts to retrieve it,
他社[たしゃ]:another company/other company, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), トライ:try, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
他社のデブリ課が
なんとかトライしていますが―
...but they all ended
in failure.
全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, 失敗[しっぱい]:failure/mistake/blunder, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
全て失敗に終わっています
So if we can snag it,
we'll be heroes.
拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather, ヒーロー:hero
うちが拾えば ヒーローってわけだ
Provides a good excuse
for a promotion, too.
昇進[しょうしん]:promotion/advancement/rising in rank, やすい:cheap/inexpensive|calm, やすい:easy|likely to .../have a tendency to ...
昇進もさせやすい… か
フィー:phi, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|
（ラビィ）フィーが係長…
Fee's gonna be a Manager...
And here I am, still only an Assistant Manager.
補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance
私だって まだ補佐なのに
おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
別に おかしくはないでしょう？
That's hardly surprising,
though.
フィー:phi, 入社[にゅうしゃ]:joining a company/getting a job with a company/entering a company
フィーさんが入社して10年―
What's strange is that Fee-san has been
with the company for ten years, and is still only
a crew leader.
今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present, 主任[しゅにん]:person in charge/senior staff/manager, 不思議[ふしぎ]:wonder/miracle/strange, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
今まで主任なのが
不思議なくらいですから
話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
でも なんで
話してくれなかったんでしょうね？
But why didn't she say anything to us?
A promotion is a big deal.
せっかく:stone burial chamber, せっかく:with trouble/at great pains|rare, 出世[しゅっせ]:success in life/getting ahead/successful career
せっかくの出世なのに
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant
管制課が嫌なんじゃないかな
Maybe she hates the thought
of moving to Control Section.
Those guys are really tense
over there, you know?
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals, ピリピリ:stinging/smarting/tingling
ほら あそこって
なんか ピリピリしてるでしょ？
Oh! Maybe you're right!
（タナベ）あっ そうですね
嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant, いくら:how much?/how many?|even, 出世[しゅっせ]:success in life/getting ahead/successful career
ハッちゃんも嫌でしょ
いくら出世できるからって
You don't want to go there, either, right Ha-chan?
Even if it means being able to climb the ranks.
出世[しゅっせ]:success in life/getting ahead/successful career, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
出世なんて
考えたこともないからな
I've never given much thought
to promotions and stuff.
It'd be okay if it meant getting your
own spaceship, though, right?
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 手に入る[てにはいる]:to obtain/to come into possession of/to get hold of
宇宙船が手に入るんなら
いいんじゃないですか？
Are you making fun
of me?
お前 バカにしてるだろ？
夢[ゆめ]:dream, それぞれ:each/respectively
まっ 夢は人それぞれってことで
Well, we all have
our own dreams.
We all have
dreams, huh?
夢[ゆめ]:dream
夢ねえ
Right! Yuri, will you act as pilot
on this new mission?
よし！ ユーリ
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, ミッション:mission, パイロット:pilot, やってくれる:to come along/to come around|to arrive at the present
今回のミッション
パイロット やってくれるか？
えっ？ ああ
Sure.
気合い[きあい]:scream/yell/fighting spirit, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
タナベ 今日は俺たちだけで出るぞ
気合い 入れろ！
Tanabe, we're going out on our own today.
Give it everything you've got.
あっ はい
Um, okay.
Fee's thinking ahead for the times
when she won't be around.
フィー:phi
フィーのやつ―
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
自分がいなくなったときのこと
考えてたんだよ
She wants to know if we can retrieve
debris by ourselves.
デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal
俺たちだけで
デブリを回収できるかって
はっ…
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, フィー:phi, さんがい:the three realms of existence|the whole universe (of a billion worlds) that Buddha enlightened, さんがい:third floor, 困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered
確かに
フィーさんがいないと困るねえ
We'd certainly be in a bind
without Fee-san...
だから 俺たちだけでやるんだよ
That's why we're going
to do this by ourselves.
We're gonna prove that we can still get the
job done even if she goes to Control Section!
フィー:phi, 管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
フィーが管制課に行っても―
やっていける:to live/to make a living/to get on with, 証明[しょうめい]:proof/verification/certification
俺たちだけで
やっていけるって証明する！
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）先輩
Senpai!
If that's the case, I suppose
we have no choice.
しかたない:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use
（ユーリ）そういうことなら
しかたないですね
Manager, we'll leave the
arm control to you.
係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, アーム:arm, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
係長 アームのほう お願いします
（ラビィ）はあ？
You're qualified to run
an arm, aren't you?
アーム:arm, 操作[そうさ]:operation/management|manipulating to one's benefit, 資格[しかく]:qualifications/requirements/capabilities, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
（ハチマキ）
アーム操作資格 持ってんだろ？
Yes, on paper!
ペーパー:paper
ペーパーなんだよ
Let's do it! This is a time for every
Debris Section worker to pull together!
やりましょう！
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew, 力を合わせる[ちからをあわせる]:to join forces/to cooperate
今こそ デブリ課全員が
力を合わせるときですよ
Right, Chief?!
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief
ねっ 課長？
ええ！？ 僕も？
Me, too?
願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself, 事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
（クレア）では お願いします
事業部長も期待していますから
I'll let you get to it, then. The division
manager has a lot riding on this, too.
Yeah, yeah...
（フィー）はいはい
What's going on here?
Our great
division manager has left?
我[われ, わ]:I|oneself|you|, 我[わが]:my/our/one's own, 事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 引き上げる[ひきあげる]:to pull up|to increase|to withdraw||
（ゲイハート）何だ 何だ
我らが事業部長は引き上げたのか
偉い[えらい]:great/excellent|awful, 重役[じゅうやく, おもやく]:company director/top management/high executive
偉そうに もう重役のつもりか
Does he think he's on the Board of Directors
already, and he's too good for us?
来客[らいきゃく, らいかく]:visitor/caller, 連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 例[れい]:custom|said|instance|, 例[ためし]:precedent/example
（部下）
来客ですよ 連合から例の
He has a visitor.
That one from INTO.
引退[いんたい]:retire, 監査役[かんさやく]:auditor/inspector, ポスト:post/position, 世話[せわ]:looking after/help/aid
ああ 引退する監査役に
ポストを世話しろってやつか
Oh, they must be forcing him to find a post
for that inspector who's retiring.
The managing director himself
is arranging it, so the division manager will
have no choice but to accept.
専務[せんむ]:special duty/being in sole charge of a duty|senior managing director, 口利き[くちきき]:mediation|influential person|eloquence|
専務の口利きですからね
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 受け入れる[うけいれる]:to accept/to receive/to agree
事業部長も
受け入れざるをえませんよ
外様[とざま]:outside daimyo/non-Tokugawa daimyo|outsider, 目立つ[めだつ]:to be conspicuous/to stand out, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
フンッ
外様のくせに目立ち過ぎるから―
He's an outsider to begin with, so we get saddled
with baggage because he stands out from the crowd.
荷物[にもつ]:luggage|burden|payload (of a packet, cell, etc.), 押し付ける[おしつける]:to press/to push/to force, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
お荷物を押し付けられるんだ
半課とかな
Baggage like Half Section.
（フィー）んん… ふん！
（クレア）んっ…
うん？
Dolf, you dumb jerk...
愚痴[ぐち]:idle complaint/grumble|moha (ignorance, folly), ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say
（フィー）ドルフのバカ！
愚痴ぐらい言えってんだ
If you don't like something,
speak up, damn it!
勝負[しょうぶ]:victory or defeat/match/contest, ゴースト:ghost, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 分間[ふんかん]:minutes (period of)
（フィー）勝負は このゴーストが
夜側の軌道にいる45分間よ
We'll make our move in the 45 minute period
of the Ghost's orbit while it's on nightside.
During that time, we'll need to detect
the target visually and retrieve it.
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 目視[もくし]:eyesight/seeing, ゴースト:ghost, 発見[はっけん]:discovery/detection/finding, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal
その間に 目視で
ゴーストを発見して回収する
At that time, we...
このとき… ん？
なんか 今日は人が多いね
There sure are a lot of people
at the briefing today...
一応[いちおう]:more or less|tentatively|just in case|, バックアップ:backup, 要員[よういん]:essential member/necessary person/personnel
（ラビィ）ああ 一応
私はバックアップ要員だから
Well, I'm technically a backup
crew member, so...
Um, I have to understand the
work that my subordinates do.
部下[ぶか]:subordinate person, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 把握[はあく]:grasp/catch/understanding
（課長）ぶ… 部下の仕事は
把握しておかないとねえ
はあ？
管理職[かんりしょく]:management, つきあい:association/socializing/socialising
いや ほら 管理職だし
何かとつきあいもねえ
Well, um, I'm management, right?
I need to act like I'm one of you.
D-Don't you worry about me.
Please continue.
あんまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry, 先に進める[さきにすすめる]:to proceed with/to continue with/to move on
うう… あんまり気にしないで
先に進めてくれないかな
Right! In this world, it's "You scratch
my back, and I'll scratch yours."
世の中[よのなか]:society/the world/the times, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
（ラビィ）そうそう 世の中
持ちつ持たれつって言うじゃない
世の中[よのなか]:society/the world/the times, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
（ラビィ）そうそう 世の中
持ちつ持たれつって言うじゃない
（フィー）ん？
O-Oh, I guess we have
a phone call.
電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device)
（課長）で… 電話かなあ？
Hello, this is Debris Section.
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（エーデル）はい デブリ課です
Yes, sir. I understand.
I'll pass that along.
伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
はい 分かりました 伝えます
フィー:phi, 管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
フィーさん 管制課から―
Fee-san, it's Control Section.
They've pushed
back the mission by six hours.
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, ミッション:mission, 遅れ[おくれ]:delay/lag/postponement
今回のミッション
６時間遅れになるそうです
Six hours, huh?
Okay, understood.
６時間ね 分かった
仮眠[かみん]:nap/doze
（課長）
じゃあ 今のうちに仮眠しない？
Why don't you use the time
to get a little sleep?
昼寝[ひるね]:nap (afternoon)/siesta
みんなで昼寝
（フィー）はあ？
Everyone should
take a nap!
提案[ていあん]:proposal/proposition/suggestion
いい提案だと思います
I think that's a good suggestion.
Concentration will be vital for this mission.
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 集中力[しゅうちゅうりょく]:(powers of) concentration/ability to concentrate, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
今回の仕事は
集中力が必要ですから
賛成[さんせい]:approval/agreement/support
賛成
（タナベ）うんうん
I agree.
まあ いいけど
Well, if you insist...
This is an official announcement.
有意義[ゆういぎ]:significant/useful/meaningful, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
（専務）今日は
有意義な話ができて よかった
I'm glad we were able to have such
a productive discussion today.
All supervisors of 7th and 9th bay operations,
please report to the Bay Office.
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
では あとのことは頼んだよ
ドルフ君
Well, I'll leave the matter
in your hands, Dolf-kun.
I'll take care of everything,
Managing Director.
任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one, 専務[せんむ]:special duty/being in sole charge of a duty|senior managing director
お任せください 専務
I repeat...
Right.
（専務）ああ
All supervisors of 7th and 9th
bay operations, please report...
寄生虫[きせいちゅう]:parasite
（ドルフ）寄生虫が…
You damn parasite...
Anyway, we need to get this finished
while Fee-kun is still asleep!
ともかく:anyhow/anyway/somehow or other, フィー:phi, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 片づける[かたづける]:to tidy up|to settle (problem)|to finish||
（ラビィ）ともかく フィー君が
寝ている間に片づけないと
We've been looking,
but there's no sign of it...
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
（タナベ）
さっきから探してるんですけどね
Are you sure the orbit calculations
aren't wrong?
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 計算[けいさん]:calculation/reckoning|forecast, 間違える[まちがえる]:to make a mistake (in)/to commit an error (e.g. in calculation)|to confuse
（ハチマキ）
軌道計算 間違えてんじゃねえの？
モニター:(computer) monitor, 映る[うつる]:to be reflected/to harmonize with (harmonise)/to come out (photo)
（課長）でも
モニターに映らないんでしょ？
It doesn't show up on our
monitors, though, right?
レーダー:radar, 映る[うつる]:to be reflected/to harmonize with (harmonise)/to come out (photo), にくい:hateful/abominable|amazing, にくい:difficult to .../hard to ...
（ユーリ）いえ
レーダーに映りにくいだけで―
No. It's nearly invisible on radar,
but it can be seen with the naked eye.
物体[ぶったい]:body/object, 物体[もったい]:superior airs/air of importance|overemphasis, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation, 可能[かのう]:potential/possible/practicable
物体として 目で確認可能です
たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however, 暗い[くらい]:dark|dark (in colour)|depressed||, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
…にしたって暗すぎてさあ
Maybe, but it's too dark
out there!
But it turns all gooey
in daylight...
昼[ひる]:noon|daytime|lunch, グニャグニャ:flabby/limp/soft and pliable
でも 昼だと グニャグニャに
なっちゃうんですよね
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, どういう:somehow/how/in what way
（社員１）
どういうことだよ ドルフ！
What's going on here, Dolf?!
Join Technora?!
Are you kidding me?!
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 冗談[じょうだん, ぎだん]:jest/joke/funny story
（社員２）テクノーラに入るなんて
冗談じゃないわ！
Is it true, Dolf?!
（フィー）本当なの？ ドルフ
（社員たち）ドルフ ドルフ！
Dolf!
- Dolf!
I'm sorry, everyone...
（ドルフ）すまん みんな
すまん
I'm sorry.
くっそ:bullshit/shit|feces, くっそ:kousso (African flowering plant, Hagenia abyssinica)/kosso/cusso, 変[へん]:strange|unexpected|change||, 思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
くっそ
変なこと思い出しちまった
Crap... Why did I have to go
dredge up that memory?
寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
ああ もう 寝てられるか
こんなときに
Damn it, how can they expect me
to sleep at a time like this?!
I see it!
（課長）あっ あった！
ありゃ:oh/ah/I'll be darned, セブン:seven
（ハチマキ）
だから ありゃ セブンだって
I keep telling you,
that's Seven.
It's over there!
（ラビィ）こっちにあるぞ
That's the D4
experiment module.
実験[じっけん]:experiment, モジュール:module
（ユーリ）
Ｄ４の実験モジュールです
あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener)
じゃあ あっちのは？
What about that, then?!
手当[てあて]:salary|medical care|advance preparation, しだい:depending on|as soon as/immediately (upon), しだい:private university or college
手当たりしだいに言えば
いいってもんじゃないだろ？
Pointing at every little thing
you see isn't helping!
いや それです
No, actually, that's it.
（ハチマキ）うっそ！？
（ラビィ）えっ！？
You're kidding!
Wow, he's right!
（タナベ）あっ 本当だ
It isn't showing up on radar,
just like the file says, so this is it.
資料[しりょう]:materials/data/document, とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light), レーダー:radar
（ユーリ）
資料のとおり レーダーには―
映る[うつる]:to be reflected/to harmonize with (harmonise)/to come out (photo)
何も映っていませんから
こいつです
I was the one who found it?
Really?!
見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing, ほんと:truth/reality|proper
僕が見つけたの？ ほんと？
That's our Chief!
Nicely done!
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 見事[みごと]:splendid|praiseworthy act|utter (esp. defeat)
さすがは課長 お見事です
（課長）うんうん…
よーし:alright/all right/right on, っきゃ:only/nothing but
よーし 行くぞ タナベ
あと 30分っきゃないんだから
Okay, Tanabe, let's get to it!
We have less than 30 minutes.
Right.
はい
（ラビィ）待て ハチ！
Hold it, Hachi!
ん？
Don't forget that you're a company man.
It's your superiors who give the orders!
サラリーマン:office worker/company employee/company man, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
自分がサラリーマンだってことを
忘れるなよ
命令[めいれい]:order/command|(software) instruction, 上司[じょうし]:superior authorities/boss, 決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes)
命令するのは
上司に決まってるだろ！
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief
さあ 課長
（課長）うん
Give the word, Chief.
Right!
Launch the Fishbone!
フィッシュ:fish, ボーン:born, 発進[はっしん]:departure/takeoff
フィッシュボーン 発進！
無駄[むだ]:futility/uselessness/pointlessness
（ハチマキ）
無駄な時間 使わせんなって
Stop wasting our time,
damn it!
Dolf... Being by yourself
is tough, isn't it?
つらい:painful/bitter|tough
（フィー）
ドルフ １人はつらいよね
（デボン）あ… あれ？
What in the world?
What, did you come by to drop off
your ferret again?
フェレット:ferret (Mustela putorius furo), 預ける[あずける]:to give into custody/to leave (a child) in the care of|to lean on
（フィー）何？
また フェレット 預けに来たの？
Um, yes, but...
ええ あっ でも…
Is everybody still
out napping?
昼寝[ひるね]:nap (afternoon)/siesta
みんな まだ昼寝してるのかな？
フィー:phi, 病気[びょうき]:illness/disease/sickness
あの… フィーさん 病気じゃ…
Um, I thought you
were sick, Fee-san...
はあ？
（エーデル）チェッ
Damn.
レンズ:lens, 光学[こうがく]:optics, 探知[たんち]:detection
（ハチマキ）
レンズは光学探知にしてるよな？
You have your lenses set on
optical detection, right?
Yes.
（タナベ）はい でも―
But I didn't expect that making a naked-eye
approach would be this hard.
目視[もくし]:eyesight/seeing, 接近[せっきん]:getting closer|being not much different|becoming close (i.e. friendly), 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
目視で接近するのが
こんなに大変なんて
ずれる:to slide/to slip off/to get dislocated, ピッチ:pitch (i.e. pace, speed, angle, space, field, sound, etc.), アップ:increasing, 度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol)
まだ ずれてます
ピッチアップ２度 ヨーライト５度
We're drifting again. Pitch up 2 degrees
Yaw right 5 degrees.
Once we get those beacons attached,
it'll be as good as ours.
信号[しんごう]:signal/signalling|traffic light, 取り付ける[とりつける]:to furnish|to get someone's agreement|to patronize
（ハチマキ）信号さえ取り付ければ
こっちのもんだけど
夜[よる, よ]:evening/night, 夜[や]:counter for nights, 終了[しゅうりょう]:end/close/termination, 切る[きる]:to cut|to sever (connections, ties)|to turn off (e.g. the light)||
夜時間終了まで
20分を切りました
You have less than 20 minutes
until nightside exit.
DS-12, report your situation.
状況[じょうきょう]:state of affairs (around you)/situation/circumstances, 報告[ほうこく]:report/information, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
DS-12 状況を報告してください
ToyBoxが出てる？
Toy Box has left
the station?!
フィー:phi, 急病[きゅうびょう]:sudden illness
（デボン）
いや フィーさん 急病だって
T-They said that you came
down with something!
うっ…
すてき:lovely/dreamy/beautiful, グッズ:goods/promotional items
すてきなノーラ君グッズね
エーデル
Gosh, that's a fine Nora pendant
that you have there, Edel.
Thank you.
はい
Senpai! I'm all done
over here!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
先輩 こっち終わりましたけど
Same here. Yuri, patch the signal
through to Control Section!
（ハチマキ）こっちもだ
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, つなぐ:to connect/to link together|to tie, つなぐ:rigging
ユーリ
管制課と通信をつないでくれ
We have a lock
on the Ghost!
ゴースト:ghost, 捉える[とらえる]:to catch|to grasp (e.g. meaning)|to captivate
ゴーストを捉えました… はっ
Orbital deviation detected. Nightside exit
in 15 minutes, 24 seconds.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 誤差[ごさ]:measurement error/calculation error, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation, 夜[よる, よ]:evening/night, 夜[や]:counter for nights, 終了[しゅうりょう]:end/close/termination, 秒[びょう]:second (60th min)
軌道誤差を確認
夜時間終了まで 15分24秒
How long?! You were off
by more than two minutes?!
誤差[ごさ]:measurement error/calculation error
何！？
２分も誤差があったってのか？
Manager, please pull it inside the cargo
container with the manipulator arm.
係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, アーム:arm, コンテナ:container (e.g. shipping)/skip, 入れ込む[いれこむ]:to put in|to be enthusiastic|to be in high spirits, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
係長 アームで
コンテナの中に入れ込んでください
係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|
係長？
Manager?
I know, I know!
Don't rush me!
せかす:to hurry/to urge on
（ラビィ）
分かってるから せかさないで！
バランスを取る[バランスをとる]:to keep balance, えぐる:to gouge/to hollow out|to greatly perturb
バランスを取って
えぐりこむように
Keep your balance.
Use a scooping motion...
そうだ 行け！
That's the way!
Go!
行き過ぎ[いきすぎ, ゆきすぎ]:going too far/going to extremes
（タナベ･ハチマキ）ああ…
（ハチマキ）行き過ぎだって
You overshot it,
damn it!
あ… あれえ？
Huh? Oh, dear...
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
んんっ… 戻ってくれー！
Come back!
あれ？
What the...?
We just generated some
secondary debris.
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, デブリ:debris, 発生[はっせい]:outbreak|generation (e.g. of power or heat)|ontogeny, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
（ユーリ）
２次デブリが発生してしまいました
（課長）どうしよう
What do we
do now?
They said they were going
to do it without you.
フィー:phi, 抜き[ぬき]:without/not including|(beating) in succession
フィーさん抜きでやるそうですよ
（フィー）ん？
Isn't this good news?
よかったですね
Control Section is more secure than retrieving
debris, and you get a pay bump, too.
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 安全[あんぜん]:safety|security, 給料[きゅうりょう]:salary/wages, 上がる[あがる]:to rise|to enter (esp. from outdoors)|to enter (a school)||
管制課なら デブリ回収より
安全だし 給料も上がるし
Those little twerps...
あいつら
やはり:too/also|still, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
（管制官）ハァ… やはり 駄目
（クレア）ええ
No good, huh?
Yes.
This is Seven. We'll let another company
deal with the secondary debris.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), セブン:seven, 次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, デブリ:debris, 他社[たしゃ]:another company/other company, 任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||
こちらセブン
２次デブリは 他社に任せます
ゴースト:ghost, 船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman, 体調[たいちょう]:physical condition, 万全[ばんぜん]:perfection/flawlessness
ゴーストも
船長の体調が万全なときの―
I recommend that you make another try for
the Ghost once your captain is back at 100%.
リトライ:retry, 勧める[すすめる]:to recommend/to advise/to encourage
リトライを勧めますが？
Uh, about that...
それは…
No, we'll do it!
（ハチマキ）いや やる
（ユーリ）ん…
We still have a signal lock, right?!
We know where it is!
信号[しんごう]:signal/signalling|traffic light, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 位置[いち]:place/situation/position
信号は生きてるんだろ？
位置は分かってんだ！
（タナベ）ああっ…
つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain, やすい:cheap/inexpensive|calm, やすい:easy|likely to .../have a tendency to ..., 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 押し込む[おしこむ]:to push into/to cram into|to break in
（ハチマキ）ラビィ
つかみやすい所まで押し込む
Lavie! I'm gonna push it to where
you can reach it easier!
Do it right this time!
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built)
今度はしっかりやってくれよ
I keep trying to tell you that
I'm only qualified on paper!
ペーパー:paper
だからさ
ペーパーだって言ってるじゃない
Of course I can't do this!
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, 決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes)
無理に決まってるって
What's with that talk?! If we give up, we won't
be able to look Fee in the eye when she leaves!
（ハチマキ）何言ってんだ！
諦める[あきらめる]:to give up/to abandon (hope, plans)/to resign oneself (to), 面[おもて, おも]:face|surface|mask (esp. a noh or kyogen mask), 面[つら]:face|surface|surrounding area|, 下げる[さげる]:to hang|to lower|to demote|, フィー:phi, 送り出す[おくりだす]:to send out/to forward/to show (a person) out
諦めたりしたら どの面下げて
フィーを送り出せってんだよ
We're gonna get the job done
by ourselves this time!
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, みせる:to show/to display
今回は
俺たちだけで やってみせるんだ
もう～
わあ！
You did it!
You lucked out!
すっげえ:incredible/unbelievable, 偶然[ぐうぜん]:coincidence|by chance|contingency (philosophy)
（ハチマキ）
やったな ハハッ すっげえ偶然！
係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 引き寄せる[ひきよせる]:to draw or pull something towards oneself (e.g. chair)
係長 そのまま引き寄せてくだ…
Okay, Manager,
now bring it...
係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 引き寄せる[ひきよせる]:to draw or pull something towards oneself (e.g. chair)
係長 そのまま引き寄せてくだ…
しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
あっ しまった
Oh, no!
やっべえ
Oh, crap!
What the hell were those
morons thinking?!
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
（フィー）
何考えてんだ あのバカどもが！
信号[しんごう]:signal/signalling|traffic light, 離れる[はなれる]:to be separated|to leave|to leave (a job, etc.)|
（クレア）うっ… 信号が離れる
The beacons are breaking loose! It's the
same mistake the other teams made!
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), チーム:team, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
他のチームと同じミスを…
DS-12!
Report your situation!
状況[じょうきょう]:state of affairs (around you)/situation/circumstances, 報告[ほうこく]:report/information, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
DS-12 状況を報告してください
We can't get a clear read
on the Ghost from here!
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), ゴースト:ghost, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation, 把握[はあく]:grasp/catch/understanding, きれる:to break/to snap|to be injured, きれる:to be able to wear/to fit into
こちらでは
ゴーストの状態を把握しきれません
Come in, Seven.
This is DS-12.
セブン:seven, こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is)
（ユーリ）セブンへ こちらDS-12
ゴースト:ghost, 液状化[えきじょうか]:liquefaction/liquefy, 本船[ほんせん]:mother ship/this ship, 要員[よういん]:essential member/necessary person/personnel
ゴーストが液状化
本船のＥＶＡ要員２名が―
The Ghost has liquefied, swallowing up two
of our EVA crew along with their work craft.
回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 作業[さぎょう]:work/operation/manufacturing, 艇[てい]:boat, ゴースト:ghost, 取り込む[とりこむ]:to take in|to capture (e.g. image)|to win over||
回収作業艇とともに
ゴーストに取り込まれました
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, グニャグニャ:flabby/limp/soft and pliable, つかめる:to seize/to catch|to obtain
駄目だ こんなグニャグニャ
つかめないよ
It's no use! I can't get
a grip on this goop!
Hey! What's it...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）先輩 ああっ
不用意[ふようい]:unpreparedness/carelessness, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||, 水中[すいちゅう]:underwater, 訓練[くんれん]:training/drill/practice, 思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
（ハチマキ）
タナベ 不用意に動くな
水中訓練を思い出せ！
Tanabe! Don't make any
careless movements!
Remember your
underwater training!
At this rate, it's going to drift farther
and farther off its estimated orbit...
計算[けいさん]:calculation/reckoning|forecast, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, どんどん:drumming (noise)|rapidly/steadily, ずれる:to slide/to slip off/to get dislocated, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
このままでは 計算軌道から
どんどんずれてしまう
Can't we rescue them?
Hey, can't we rescue them?!
助かる[たすかる]:to be saved|to escape harm|to be helped
助からないの？
ねえ 助からないの？ ユーちゃん
Yuri-chan!
外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 操縦[そうじゅう]:steering/piloting|management, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
私が外に出ます
ToyBoxの操縦 お願いします
I'm going outside.
You have control of Toy Box.
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, ハンドル:handle
ちょ ちょっと 無理だよ
僕は車のハンドルだって―
W-Wait, I can't do that! My wife doesn't even
let me get behind the wheel of a car!
妻[つま]:wife|my dear|garnish (esp. one served with sashimi)|, 妻[め]:female/woman|wife, 握らす[にぎらす]:to let (someone) take hold of your hand, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me), くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
妻に握らして
もらえないくらいなんだよ
She doesn't even let me
drive used cars!
中古車[ちゅうこしゃ]:used car/secondhand car, 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
中古車だって
許してもらえないんだ
しかし このままでは…
- But if we don't do something,
they'll...
Yuri, get back
in your seat!
席[せき]:seat|location (of a gathering, etc.)|position, 席[むしろ, えん]:woven mat (esp. one made of straw)|seat, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
（フィー）ユーリ 席に戻って
（ユーリ）なっ
（課長）えっ
フィー:phi
（ハチマキ）フィーか
Is that Fee?
急病[きゅうびょう]:sudden illness
あなた 急病だったんじゃ…
I thought you were sick!
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action), 微速[びそく]:very slow speed, 前進[ぜんしん]:advance/drive/progress, 秒[びょう]:second (60th min), メートル:metre/meter
軌道方向 微速前進
秒 12メートル 増速
Move slowly ahead along your trajectory.
Accelerate 12 meters per second.
Move ahead of the Ghost and use
Toy Box to cast a shadow.
一旦[いったん]:once|for a short time|one morning, ゴースト:ghost, 追い越す[おいこす]:to pass (e.g. car)/to overtake|to surpass, 影[かげ]:shadow|reflection|ominous sign||, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
一旦 ゴーストを追い越して
ToyBoxで影を作って
旧式[きゅうしき]:old type/old style, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great
そうか
旧式のToyBoxは大きいから
Right! An old ship like
Toy Box is huge!
It should be plenty big enough
to cover the Ghost.
十[じゅう, とお]:ten, 十[シー]:ten, ゴースト:ghost, 覆う[おおう]:to cover/to hide/to conceal, きれる:to break/to snap|to be injured, きれる:to be able to wear/to fit into
（フィー）
十分 ゴーストを覆いきれるはずよ
縮む[ちぢむ, ちじむ]:to shrink/to contract/to diminish (in size), じゃう:to do something completely
（タナベ）でも そうすると
縮んじゃいますよね？ これ
But it'll shrink when you
do that, won't it?!
心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care, デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, スーツ:suit
（フィー）心配するな
デブリ回収用のスーツだろ
Don't worry, those are debris recovery suits.
The specs say we'll be able to handle it.
データ:data/datum, 耐える[たえる]:to bear|to support|to be fit for
データ上は耐えられる
The important thing is for you and Hachi
to move to the Ghost's edge.
ゴースト:ghost, 端[そば, そく]:near/close|third person, 端[はし, はじ]:end (e.g. of street)|beginning|odds and ends
それより
ハチとタナベは ゴーストの端に
Stick as much as you can outside the Ghost
while it's liquefied, even if it's just your left arms.
液状[えきじょう]:liquid state, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 左腕[さわん, ひだりうで]:left arm|left-handed (baseball pitcher), 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|
液状になってる間に
左腕だけでも 外に出すんだ
Right. Can you do that,
Tanabe?
（ハチマキ）
よし できるな？ タナベ
（タナベ）はい
Yes.
Lavie, put the arm in a horizontal position.
Increase the shadow area as much as possible.
アーム:arm, 横[よこ]:horizontal (as opposed to vertical)|side-to-side (as opposed to front-to-back)|side (of a box, etc.)||, 位置[いち]:place/situation/position
（フィー）
ラビィは アームを横位置に
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 影[かげ]:shadow|reflection|ominous sign||, 面積[めんせき]:square measure/size (e.g. of land)/area, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
少しでも影面積を取って
分かりました
Understood!
And last comes you, Chief.
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief
（フィー）最後に課長
（課長）はい
Yes?
コピー:copy/photocopy
（フィー）何もしないで
（課長）アイ コピー
Don't do anything.
I copy!
船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman, 代理[だいり]:representation/agency/proxy
船長は代理なんですよ？
できると思っているんですか？
The man at the helm is just a stand-in!
Do you really think he can do this?
Even if you're in Control Section, you're still
part of the debris recovery team.
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
管制課ではあっても―
デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, チーム:team
あなたも
デブリ回収チームの仲間でしょ？
はあ？
If you don't believe in your teammates,
you'll never get anywhere.
信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in, 始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from)
仲間を信じなきゃ
何も始まらないって
（クレア）あ…
Wow, that was close!
危[き]:danger|Chinese "rooftop" constellation (one of the 28 mansions)
危ねえ ギリッギリ
タナベは？
What about you,
Tanabe?!
I'm sorry, I wasn't
able to make it out!
（タナベ）すいません
出られませんでした
重心[じゅうしん]:centre of gravity (center)|centroid|(one's) balance, 方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action), 秒[びょう]:second (60th min), 噴射[ふんしゃ]:jet/spray/injection
ハチ 重心方向に 10秒噴射
- Hachi!
Fire a ten-second thrust
along your center of gravity!
You got it!
（ハチマキ）あいよ
アーム:arm, 押し込む[おしこむ]:to push into/to cram into|to break in
（フィー）
ラビィ アームで押し込みな
Lavie, try pushing it in
with the arm!
（ラビィ）は… はい
Y-Yes, ma'am!
Switch channel G8
back to auto.
チャンネル:channel, オート:auto/automobile/automatic, 戻す[もどす]:to put back|to vomit|to recover (of a market price)
（フィー）
チャンネルＧ８ オートで戻す
（ラビィ）はい
Yes, ma'am!
引っ張る[ひっぱる]:to pull|to string (lines)|to pull towards oneself (e.g. someone's sleeve)||, 込む[こむ]:to be crowded|to be complex|to go into||, コンテナ:container (e.g. shipping)/skip, 閉じる[とじる]:to close (e.g. book, eyes, meeting, etc.)/to shut
ＯＫ そのまま引っ張り込んで
ユーリ コンテナを閉じる
Okay, keep pulling
it towards you.
Yuri! Close the
cargo container!
Understood.
（ユーリ）分かりました
And... okay!
Retrieval complete!
よーし:alright/all right/right on, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 完了[かんりょう]:completion/conclusion|perfect (tense, form, aspect), 完了[ワンラ]:end/completion
よーし 回収完了
We did it!
やったー！
成功[せいこう]:success/hit
成功したの？ 成功したの？
Did we do it?
幽霊[ゆうれい]:ghost/specter/spectre, 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize, 私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us
ハッハー！ 幽霊を捕まえましたよ
この私たちが
We caught that boogie man!
We caught it!
よかった 本当に
Thank goodness...
おーい:hey!/oi!|I
（ハチマキ）おーい
Hey!
コンテナ:container (e.g. shipping)/skip, 内[うち]:inside|while|among||, 内[ない]:inside/within, 温度[おんど]:temperature, 上げる[あげる]:to raise|to do up (one's hair)|to fly (a kite, etc.)||, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
コンテナ内の温度上げてくれよ
動けないんだよ
Raise the temperature in the
cargo container! I can't move!
気を抜く[きをぬく]:to lose focus/to let one's mind wander/to relax one's attention, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
みんな 気を抜くのは まだ早いよ
It's too early to start celebrating
just yet, people.
A debris hauler's job isn't done
until it's hauled back to base.
デブリ:debris, 持ち帰る[もちかえる]:to bring back/to carry home/to take out (e.g. food), 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
デブリを持ち帰るまでが
デブリ屋の仕事だからね
コピー:copy/photocopy
ユー コピー？
You copy?
We copy!
コピー:copy/photocopy
（ハチマキたち）ウィ コピー
Hey, Tanabe, you okay?
（ハチマキ）
おい タナベ 大丈夫か？
Yes, I think.
（タナベ）はい なんとか
Look sharp!
（ハチマキ）
シャッキリしろ！ 俺たちは―
We grabbed the Ghost, a piece of debris
that no other debris section could catch.
デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather, ゴースト:ghost, 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize
よそのデブリ屋が拾えなかった
ゴーストを捕まえたんだぞ！
はい でも…
（ハチマキ）ああ？
Yes, but...
This means that Fee-san's
gonna leave, isn't it?
フィー:phi
これで フィーさん
行っちゃうんですね
（ハチマキ）あっ…
Yeah, I guess it does.
ああ そうだな
（管制官）EBR-068-2114R…
DBR-068-2114
is extremely...
So, I hear you had to hire
a retired INTO bureaucrat, huh?
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 天下り[あまくだり]:retiring high-ranking government officials taking a lucrative job in a private or semi-private corporation|command (from superior to inferior, government to private sector, etc.)|descent from heaven, 受け入れる[うけいれる]:to accept/to receive/to agree
（フィー）聞いたわ 連合から
天下りを受け入れるんだって？
If you consider the big picture,
it ends up as a plus for us.
トータル:total, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, プラス:plus/addition
（ドルフ）
トータルで考えれば プラスになる
You're not happy
with it?
気に入る[きにいる]:to be pleased with/to suit
気に入らないか？
（フィー）そうね
I guess not.
栄転[えいてん]:promotion, 辞退[じたい]:declining/refusal/nonacceptance
だから 栄転を辞退したのか？
That's why you turned down
the promotion?
No, it's not. I want to stay
out in the field, that's all.
現場[げんば, げんじょう]:actual spot/scene|shop floor
違うわ 私は現場にいたいだけ
我々[われわれ]:we, 生活[せいかつ]:living/life (one's daily existence)/livelihood, 今更[いまさら]:now (after such a long time)/at this late hour (i.e. it is too late for something)|afresh, 後戻り[あともどり]:going backward/turning back|retrogression
（ドルフ）我々の生活は
今更 後戻りはできない
There's no turning back from
humanity's new way of life.
And we have to rely on space for the
energy to support that way of life.
エネルギー:energy, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 頼る[たよる]:to rely on/to have recourse to/to depend on
そして そのためのエネルギーは
宇宙に頼るしか すべがない
Space development requires
that you work on a large scale.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, スケール:scale/vernier, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
宇宙開発には スケールが必要だ
Funding. Organization. Political clout.
資金[しきん]:funds/capital, 組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 政治力[せいじりょく]:political strength
資金 組織 政治力
飲み込む[のみこむ]:to gulp down|to understand|to engulf||
それがなければ
別の何かに飲み込まれる
Without those, you get
swallowed up by another entity.
Just like our
company did?
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
（フィー）私たちの会社みたいに？
我々[われわれ]:we, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
（ドルフ）だから 我々は
変わらなければならない
That is why we
have to change.
You. And me.
君も 私も
フッ…
Dolf, you haven't
changed one bit.
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
ドルフ あなたは変わっていないわ
Yes, I have.
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
変わったさ
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
（フィー）
変わったように見えるだけ
You only look like
you've changed.
Spend some time in the sun, and you'll
turn back into your old self.
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 浴びる[あびる]:to dash over oneself (e.g. water)/to take (e.g. shower)|to suffer (e.g. an attack), 元[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 元[げん]:unknown (e.g. in an equation)|element (of a set)|yuan (monetary unit of China)|, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
光を浴びれば すぐに元に戻るわ
チーム:team, 組む[くむ]:to cross (legs or arms)|to put together|to braid||
私は 今もあなたと
チームを組んでるつもりよ
I like to think that you and I
are still on the same team.
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 駆け上がる[かけあがる]:to run up (a hill, stairs etc.)/to dash up/to rush up
光の当たる場所まで
早く駆け上がって
Claw your way back up into the light.
Back to where you can be yourself again.
元[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 元[げん]:unknown (e.g. in an equation)|element (of a set)|yuan (monetary unit of China)|, 姿[すがた]:figure|appearance|state||, 取り戻す[とりもどす]:to take back/to regain/to get back, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
あなたが
元の姿を取り戻せる場所まで
安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice, 働く[はたらく]:to work|to function|to commit (e.g. a crime)|
そうなれば 私も安心して働ける
Do that, and I'll be able to do my job
with some peace of mind.
Right?
ねっ？
うん
コピー:copy/photocopy
フッ… ユー コピー？
You copy?
♪～
飲み干す[のみほす]:to drink up/to drain (cup)
♪グッと水を飲み干し
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset), 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
街路樹[がいろじゅ]:roadside trees, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood), テンパる:to become one tile away from completion|to be at one's wits' end/to be about to blow one's fuse
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, つまずく:to stumble/to trip|to fail
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
気楽[きらく]:carefree/comfortable|easygoing
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
愛する[あいする]:to love, 勇気[ゆうき]:courage/bravery/valour, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
歩く[あるく]:to walk
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
喜び[よろこび]:joy/delight/rapture, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), つづける:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Next Time
Regrets
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 保安庁[ほあんちょう]:National Security Board (1952-1954)
（ギガルト）
軌道保安庁の―
Gigalt Gungulgash of the
Orbital Security Agency.
ギガルト･
ガンガラガッシュだ
この～
Why, you...!
んぐぅ…
（ハチマキ）うわーっ
ぷはー
（リュシー）タナベ！
Tanabe!
予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule
その日は予定が入ってて
I have plans
that day.
（ハチマキ）そっか
Oh, I see.
野菜[やさい]:vegetable, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||, 何度[なんど]:how many times?/how often?
（ギガルト）野菜を取れと
何度 言ったら分かるんだ
How many times do I have to tell you
to eat your veggies?!
ん…
What's with you? You got a problem with it?
文句[もんく]:complaint/grumbling|phrase, でもある:to also be (formal, literary)/implies that as well as the earlier stated this is also the case|to be ... or something
何だよ
何か文句でもあるのか？
じゃあ 違うんですか？
You think I'm wrong?
どっち:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives)
（ハチマキ）
どっちでもいいだろ？
It doesn't matter
either way, right?
ハチマキ:headband, ご覧[ごらん]:(please) try to|(please) look|seeing, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（ギガルト）ハチマキ！
（ラビィ）ご覧くださーい
Hachimaki!
Take a look... at these!